[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software this is a new one for
soft engineering radio today I have with
me Andrew Phillips he heads up product
management xeb ellipse andrew is an
evangelist and thought leader in the
DevOps cloud and application release
automation space he sits on the
management team of Samuel Epps and tries
product Direction positioning and
planning today I will be talking with
Andrew about DevOps
Andrew welcome to the show Thank You Sue
Anne I'm glad to be here that makes me
sound so kind of important I like to
joke that I mean yes officially I'm the
VP of product but just so people don't
get concerned and think I can only make
PowerPoint presentations I also try and
spend a lot of my time like remembering
what we're real life is like so I am a
member of the Apache Software Foundation
I work on a bunch of open-source
projects I collect scholar puzzlers so
from time to time usually between like
10:00 and 2:00 in the morning
I actually manage to get my hands dirty
and do real stuff and luckily my
girlfriend's a software developer so she
she kind of understands okay good
what projects at that patchy fog
currently the VP for Apache J clouds and
I've worked on a bunch of other things
in the past I worked a bit on multiverse
which was an original software
transactional memory system that was
inside acha acha as i don't want to
pronounce it I can't pronounce it
properly Yanis poner will have to do
that just it's a Scala and Java library
and IV I've committed a few things to
things like Gradle and a few other of
the bigger open-source projects I have
my name on some of the commits in the
Scala source code it's ok ok let's get
started what is DevOps mmm how much time
do we have 50 minutes ok well let's try
and keep it short then I mean I think
the big problem today is that
actually if you're coming at this space
very new it's almost impossible to get a
a sane and simple answer to this
question because of course so many
people are jumping onto this bandwagon
and trying to trying to claim that it's
their own I sometimes like to joke that
you know if you make a screwdriver
nowadays and it's for installing racks
people will call it a DevOps screwdriver
so from my perspective in terms of
trying to keep it simple what I would
say is that it's basically an attempt to
try to understand that the world of
software development goes beyond like
just writing the code if you like it's
taking those agile principles that we've
mainly adopted in the industry now and
realizing that the scrum board extends
beyond where it typically goes it
actually goes into how do I get this new
piece of code out into production so I
mean one of the original formulations in
fact that the famous original post-it
note of the conference was agile
operations and so I think having that in
mind is a kind of you know applying
agile principles to operations is a good
way to think about this I think you know
more generally anybody who's worked
you've got their hands dirty with
software development realizes that a lot
of the problems that we face come from
the fact that no development and
operations and of course other groups as
well QA and security and so on really
don't know enough about what the other
group does it's very common in
organization step operations teams
trying to run applications that they do
not understand at all they don't know
what they does who the users are roughly
how the application works
and similarly developers and plenty of
developers who only know how to set up
the system on their laptop and have no
idea what the overall production
architecture looks like and these things
cause plenty of problems and so people
who've had to live on both sides of the
fence realize that we can make stuff a
lot better by having more mutual
understanding and that's really I think
ultimately where DevOps comes from and
what it tries to do so that sounds that
DevOps has a relationship to lean yeah
I'm done sorry
Doan I thought you you you weren't
finished with your question yeah
because Lim says where we have to look
at the the whole value chain and yeah if
you only look at for instance scrum
scrum stops at delivering features and
it doesn't bring anything into
production so yeah we have a bottleneck
exactly and I think I mean so I think
you're right and I think especially what
we've seen over there over the past few
years is the convergence of a lot of
terms that actually look at this process
more fundamentally whether it's
continuous delivery or lean and I'm sure
we'll get into that in a bit more detail
I think the origins are a little
different I mean lean makes the process
very explicit and very first class I
think a lot of the drivers of DevOps
originally and that has changed over the
years we're almost emotional they were
like you know we're suffering together
and we can make our lives better and I
think in a lot of cases if you asked the
the original proponents of DevOps what
are you actually trying to do they
wouldn't necessarily have turned around
and said we want to optimize the
end-to-end process of software delivery
that's really what continuous delivery
and lean to some extent were all about
it was more like we are suffering a lot
because we don't work together enough
and and we can make this better by
collaborating more but of course over
the years as companies especially and
vendors and analysts have tried to make
DevOps more business friendly and to try
to attach very concrete like no return
on investment kind of terms to it you
know the idea that is the sort of hippie
style language if we go cuddle each
other more than life will get better
that doesn't sound very compelling to a
CIO so you have to attach all these very
concrete metrics to it things like you
know accelerating time to market
reducing waste yada yada yada and
especially where once you start to bring
those kind of terms it becomes very
difficult to distinguish something like
DevOps from continuous delivery or lean
indeed okay what are them did the goals
of of DevOps hmm so I mean yeah without
trying to repeat myself too much I think
originally the goal was was genuinely
trying to feel like make life
better for the people at the coalface
for both development and operation by
increasing mutual understanding and the
also mutual trust and collaboration
because once you get a picture for what
used to be the enemy you can find better
ways of working together and of helping
each other I think if you look at you
know if you pick up I don't know a
Gartner sheet or you read some of the
blog post so that the white papers
nowadays people will say more likely
that the goal of DevOps is like to
accelerate time to market to reduce
costs to reduce error rates to speed up
innovation these kind of very
business-friendly terms
I don't think that necessarily was the
original goal but I think that's the
goal as its presented often nowadays in
practice what happens a lot is that
people recast the goal of DevOps as
being we need to introduce 5,000
automation tools because you know once
you know the goals are very you know
easy to state but of course what people
need to do if they now decide that this
sounds greater than they want to adopt
DevOps they need to figure out well what
do I have to do now where do I start and
very often the most visible part of a
DevOps implementation is the use of a
whole bunch of very cool tools you know
whether it's puppet or share for nagios
or AppDynamics or dyeing whatever those
are the very kind of obvious visible
things and so people tend to pick those
as being the things that they're going
to get started with but I am always one
who's very careful to state like tooling
and automation is not a goal of DevOps
it might be something you want to do to
help achieve what you're trying to
achieve but it's really a means to an
end and not the end in itself you
mentioned that most companies then start
with buying tools if they they want to
do DevOps and and that's obviously wrong
but what is riot how should I get
started well and there I think bliing
actually you know has one of the best
and most obvious prescriptions for how
they get started I've sometimes
certainly recently when talking to
people who ask me this question I say
let's ignore all the terminology what do
you actually want to achieve and I think
the interesting thing is that the goals
once you really start asking about them
they're not generic no they really
depend on the kind of company you in the
context you're working in I mean I can
talk about ourselves is a very trivial
example like we're a software vendor we
write software tools of course we want
to optimize the process of delivering
our tools as well as little friction as
possible in the development and delivery
process but our customers would not want
to release every five minutes because
they run the software on premise out a
new update every five minutes they would
go crazy similarly there's a very
interesting presentation by a CIO from
GE Capital and he said look the goals
that they chose for their DevOps
initiative were no faster whiteboard -
production time as they termed it so
taking ideas and getting them actually
to their users the whiteboard the
production time I think a lower error
rate was what he was mentioning like
getting it end-to-end without breaking
so often and the third one which was
very interesting was reducing the time
it takes to provide audit answers and
this is I think an interesting example
of a very industry specific problem like
if you're in retail for instance
answering questions from auditors isn't
a big pain point for you in general but
if you're in the financial world it's a
really big problem
and so they deliberately engineered
their process and their tool choices in
the collaboration and the security model
and so on to allow them to optimize for
this problem so I think I mean of course
it's it's it's a very scary kind of
consulting answer to say well it depends
what's the right way to do it I think
the right way to do it is indeed to
start with a clear and share definition
of what you're trying to achieve what
are the metrics that were actually
trying to optimize for and then I think
you know the the notion of a value
stream mapping in the way lean does it
is a very good way to start now you
actually try to understand what do we do
today from taking an idea and actually
getting it running in production
because ironically in a lot of
organizations you'll find that nobody
has the full picture like people the
developers know how its developed and
maybe the release team knows how it's
released
but that whole end-to-end picture is
often missing once you have a 1020 on
this rain is getting really loud so
maybe we should move somewhere else but
once you have that n2 in picture then
you can start to see what the waste is
and you can also start to see where do
we need to actually optimize in practice
as I think I mean so this I think this
is the right way to do it I think the
challenge with that is that it it can be
very scary for organisations to take
such a big scope because in you know if
you go to a big organization production
may be run by an outsourced company
development may be partially outsourced
depending on which systems you're
talking about there's all kinds of
different departments involved so to
take this really high-level view it's a
very difficult thing to do if you're
trying to grow and start small you
really need to take this sort of
enterprise transformation a concept and
that's very scary for a lot of big
companies so typically if I talk about
what's realistic to do in a small
environment
yeah obviously pick a couple of you know
projects or teams and then the team
itself will probably have a pretty good
idea of what's going wrong right now you
know how long does it take them to
deploy an application how long does it
take them to spin up a testing
environment what's the error rate going
forward to production bla bla bla bla so
without doing any really complicated
analyses you can pretty quickly identify
what the big problems are and you can
typically pick tools to try to help with
those now tooling isn't always the
solution to these problems but by and
large the vast majority of problems that
people are facing in this overall chain
can be made better by tools I mean is
you know if you're still sending an
email to someone in a different
department to please pick up this binary
from a shared folder and copied onto a
production server it's pretty clear that
that process can easily be optimized and
yeah so I think I mean it's it sounds
ridiculous to say to imagine that that
is the status quo but I think by and
large that for a lot of people that is
the status quo okay you mentioned
you stream analysis that sounds also
like value stream analysis is a typical
lean tool right so that is then also
commonality yeah okay and you mentioned
one of the and the goal is to bring
whiteboard ideas into production that's
I wrote that quite often from the
continuous delivery Kemp what's the
relationship between DevOps and
continuous delivery is it the same well
it's alright let me let me answer this
in two ways unfortunately I think for
for the vast majority of people who are
entering the space today and who haven't
been through the sort of five years of
development of the two terms the easiest
way to understand it is to claim that or
to just accept that people use the terms
almost interchangeably now some people
say continuous delivery is the goal of
DevOps some people say DevOps is the key
thing you need to do to get continuous
delivery running I don't think either of
them are necessarily quote unquote true
if you go back to the original origins
but frankly it's it's almost not worth
arguing that point because ultimately
you know what the majority messaging is
to some extent that is what people will
hear so I think nowadays unfortunately
these terms are used almost synonymously
I think I mean this is some of the
things that that continuous delivery is
a fairly prescriptive process-oriented
framework
it doesn't really if you read the book
if you like it doesn't talk all that
much about you know how collaboration
between departments produces a better
environment for all it says look really
what we care about is optimizing the
end-to-end process so that you can
release smaller batches of changes more
efficiently more quickly and that has
all the benefits that we've all heard
about it reduces the risk it allows you
to innovate faster everything is perfect
right obviously not quite true but but I
think that's the sort of bigger picture
there and very often people that have
tried to implement this end-to-end
process realize and this gets into the
whole kind of systems thinking type ID
once you start to explicitly talk about
the end-to-end pipeline or process you
realize that you basically need to have
everybody who's involved understanding
the process so you're you're pretty
quickly at the kind of product team
concept or systems-thinking concept I
think some of the things that are not
typically talked about in a continuous
delivery environment but they do very
well from from my perspective very much
part of like DevOps thinking is the
notion that you know we're all friends
to some extent not just because that's
more efficient but because we're
actually all writing software at
different parts of the stack we all have
you know techniques that can basically
be applied to each other and actually
pretending you know if we're different
and we're sort of enemies is not really
helping anybody I mean let's face it but
maybe the biggest change in the past 10
years in operations is not something
like DevOps or continuous delivery it's
simply the fact that we have shifted
from a fit being a physical logistical
job of actually moving boxes around and
installing them in data centers and
stuff like that
operations nowadays is largely a
software development job like all the
stuff you're doing is virtual you're
defining virtual servers virtual
networks virtual bridges virtual DNS all
this kind of stuff and so obviously all
the things that we've spent 15 20 30
years learning from Abdera quote-unquote
software development things like in unit
testing continuous integration
modularization they all apply to modern
day operational development as well so
since we're both doing development to
some extent it doesn't make sense to say
well we're not going to share
experiences here and so I think you know
a lot of the things I like to either
there's a few questions I used to like
to ask when people say like we do DevOps
I didn't I typically did not try to ask
about tooling I would ask things like
you know when was the last time your
average app developer had a beer with
someone for operations or how easy is it
in your organization to
have your production DBA sitting in a
planning meeting or a sprint review or
something so that they can help you
understand you know something like a
very treatment simple practical example
you're building your de system on your
laptop based on the assumption that your
database lives on the same system so the
latency is very very low if you
understand it in your production
environment your database may be in
another data center with a certain level
of latency in between that obviously can
have an impact on how you architect and
develop your application but this is the
kind of like simple shared knowledge
that in many cases isn't present and
then you get into the the classic
problem that you run a low test in the
pre-production environment one day
before you're due to go live and you
discover that the application just falls
apart because it's making 10,000 queries
and each of them takes half a second to
respond or whatever yeah yeah so I mean
DevOps I think originally was very much
about look we've learned that this
happens in real life what can we do at
the process level at the human level
also at the tooling level to try to
eliminate these problems okay so it's
basically bringing every technically
responsible person for the end-to-end
process in more or less one room or into
one team exactly and I think because
once I mean that's why I think
ultimately if you start to think enough
about all of them they all converge to
the same thing because even if you start
with a team you bring all the people
into a room well what do you end up
talking about you end up talking about
the end-to-end process similarly if you
start with the goal of the end-to-end
process which is where continuous
delivery would start from and you then
figure out well what does it take to
understand and optimize this end-to-end
process pretty quickly you need to
figure out you have all the people in
the room so you you end up with kind of
the same point and I think that's what
we're seeing right now and of course
ironically with agile it's kind of the
same thing I mean people nowadays talk
of continuous delivery and agile as if
they were two things but one of the the
slides I like to put up in my
presentations is the following quote
like the most important thing is the
continuous delivery of valuable software
to our customer
and that's principle number one from the
agile manifesto hmm so you know it's not
like version 2 of agile it's actually
right in there in version 1 it's just
that of course most people don't do this
because agile started out within the
development department and it sort of
stopped where their quote unquote
boundaries of the development department
tended to stop now exactly yeah I that's
what I heard quite often that DevOps is
actually post agonism so we had address
off a development but it stopped after
you know accepted features yeah but then
it has to go somehow in production and
that was then of obviously a problem
because we had barriers and these bury
their folks just broke that barriers
down yeah and I think then of who hurts
the the CTO of Emerson he once said that
the teams at Amazon they have a simple
rule they built the software and the the
same team which builds the software also
runs the software so you build it you
run it that's one of his famous quotes
and and and that is basically an early
death of Steve right yeah I mean really
DevOps teams of course this goes way
back like think back to mainframe
development they built it and run it as
well so I mean to some extent this is
nothing new
we've historically and for lots of types
of very specialist systems there was
never this distinction between building
and running because the people who had
the expertise to build stuff were also
the people who ended up running it it's
only as we started to if you like
consider operations as some kind of out
sourced
separate function like a utility which
would take care of all the underlying
stuff and then then we would just shove
applications into there and they didn't
really matter whether the team that that
provided the foundation really
understood about the application that
this started to get split and of course
yes as you say you know it's that that
classic you build that you run it or you
get the pager those kind of things they
immediately force people to think about
the operational aspects like very know
one of the examples from Amazon is it's
very classic and this is a sort of
classic
DevOps metric if you like that as soon
as you start to get the thing that wakes
you up at 3:00 in the morning the number
of logging statements and the number of
like operation as supporting features in
your code like health check pages and
all this kind of stuff goes up
dramatically and and of course the in
one easy way to enforce this is to make
the developers feel the pain but even if
you're not in a position to do that
because of course for a lot of
organizations the development might be
outsourced or you know they're working
in a timezone that is different from
your customer so it's very difficult to
get them to do production support or
whatever you can still try to ignore
it's a very important metric so you can
always ask yourself how easy is it in
your organization for somebody from
operations to actually put a feature
request on the backlog of a development
team and say look we're really
struggling with your application because
when it goes down we have zero idea of
what's going on now it's a very common
problem and to what extent is your
organization able to address it like
even if they do put in a feature is
there any chance of it ever getting
implemented you know these kind of
things are very good examples for how
much you you regard the building and
running of a system as being two sides
of the same coin as opposed to totally
separate problems and we talked about
Amazon and what DevOps means to to them
but I can imagine that different
companies do understand different things
about DevOps so I think you also
mentioned that different companies have
different problems they sort of can you
give a few examples yeah sure I think
unfortunately the biggest class I mean
just like it's just like with that gel
like we're not we're seeing the same
kind of evolution you know with agile I
think I don't know what the exact
estimates right now are but but agile is
supposedly the majority software
development methodology in the world
more than 50% of projects are run this
way but I think we all know that
probably at least 49% of those projects
when they say agile they mean we have a
scrum board and we
lots of money for post-it notes and we
stand up at 8 o'clock in the morning
rather than you know sitting down but
otherwise we effectively have a
waterfall process it said except for etc
so one of the problems with any kind of
strategy or any kind of philosophy
almost methodology like DevOps or agile
is that adopting it late usually means
you try to look at what the people who
are supposedly doing it successfully of
doing and you just copycat what they're
doing so yes you will install puppet
chef and then you will get Jenkins and
you might you know whatever you might
install I don't know HipChat or
something and suddenly you think you're
doing DevOps but that's not you know the
vast majority of DevOps implementations
look like this and I don't think that's
the fault of the companies I mean I
think that's part of the challenge for
the industry is to because because the
reaction to this is usually the people
say yes yes but of course you're not
supposed to copy us you're supposed to
learn the way we think yeah I think that
is that's a very interesting point I
read a lot of lean publications and they
also say they see Toyota or they see
what Toyota is doing in the US and they
they say ok we perfectly copy what they
do to our production plant and it's it
just goes horribly wrong and for the
same reasons you say it's you it's not a
cookbook exactly and I mean I think a
lot and I think as you know as people
trying to promote this concept in the
space we have two duties one to point
out that it's not a cookbook but that is
only partially helpful because let's
face it most people who work for large
organizations not stupid
it's not that they they don't know this
it's just that you know if you haven't
been deeply involved in the field you
can't just sort of absorb the thinking
of a field by reading a book in a couple
of days right it's time and practice and
of course a lot of the if you like the
the picture that sort of textbook
examples of companies don't have a lot
of the challenges that big companies
have like so one of the classic comments
we always get is like yes sure Etsy or
Amazon or Facebook or whatever no that's
not the environment that
95% of these other companies are working
in and all the companies we I've just
mentioned have looked at tremendous
abundance of technical talent you know
the notion of having to work with people
who maybe aren't the the smartest or
whatever that doesn't exist there that
there's not that much of a struggle to
hold on to good people you can trust
them to wrestle their way around every
tool that they come across you can trust
them to write their own tools if
necessary and the organizations are
pretty young and pretty flexible that is
not the situation that a bank for
instance is typically in like you know
they don't have to deal with eight
different vendors running different
systems systems that have been around
for thirty five years with only three
people who still understand how they
work difficulty retaining talent etc etc
so I think it's not just about saying
you know don't believe in a cookbook
it's also about trying to understand
well how can we make it easy for you to
understand what you should be doing and
I think to me the big the big lesson I
mean to some extent I already said some
of this the first is to recognize that
in whatever pretty much whatever
industry you're in largely both
development and operations are basically
doing software development so make sure
you know they you apply the same kind of
lessons to both and then you as an
organization I think right now you have
a choice you have a choice to try to
merge those two development streams
together to do the kind of full stack
deployment model which is something you
know companies like Facebook or Netflix
are typical examples of basically there
is no more distinction between the the
platform on which your stuff runs and
the application it's just a big
deliverable like version 3.5 of my
system and that is everything from the
operating systems and the networks and
the DNS settings all the way through
issue code and the stuff on top of that
and in the other model which which also
be companies I mean so Google for
instance at Google as a developer you
have no idea how your stuff runs in
production it just works
it goes in some container you don't see
it magic brilliant if you're a developer
because it just works
but there's a very distinct split there
I think you did as a company you need to
make that kind of decision and I think
the other thing you need to do as a
company is to every company recognizes
immediately that if there were a better
communication and a better understanding
between development and operations and
security and QA of course and all these
other departments things could be better
but I think that the way every company
should perhaps best approaches and this
gets back a little bit to the value
stream mapping well what are the three
biggest problems like what do they know
is it that the developers don't
understand how the thing runs in
production is it that developers don't
have any idea of the security
requirements that need to be met is it
that the systems that you build other
totally unorder table because of all
these manual processes that are doing
and that that's a big pain point and
once you understand where the biggest
knowledge gaps are most companies have
you know have a pretty good idea of what
could be done to fix them that doesn't
mean that that is possible because in
some cases it might mean you have to
like fly people halfway across the world
every two weeks and that's unlikely to
be feasible but I think if you regard
DevOps
as you know DevOps is a way of you know
trying to identify and tackle the
biggest problems resulting from you know
mismatches in understanding and end
process between development security QA
operations and so on then you also have
a pretty good blueprint for what you
need to do to fix it because I can't
tell me you as a company what your three
biggest problems are I can tell you what
you should look for but you need to
identify those problems themselves and
then of course once you've identified
the problems sure I can come with some
experience about how other companies
have tried to tackle these problems in
the past and then you know rather than
having to do the heavy lifting of trying
to identify possible solutions then we
can say yeah you know you might want to
look at this tool or you might want to
look at this technique or whatever so I
think I think that's a that's a good way
of starting you know think of this as
identify the biggest knowledge gaps the
biggest process gaps in that overall
system that end-to-end process
and then figure out which are the ones
that you can realistically solve solve
all of them at the same time but is
there a specific culture needed to
succeed with DevOps
is there a specific culture that's
needed to achieve any kind of vision I
think I think the one thing that is the
perhaps the most important is that you
know you're never going to it's going to
be very difficult for people to be
motivated to solve what's essentially an
end-to-end problem if your organization
is very well not say negative but it
buddy it's not very it doesn't foster
and think if you are in an organ in the
classic example being if you're in an
organization where you know an operator
is paid or given a bonus purely on the
percentage of uptime and the developer
is paid based on the number of new
features that are delivered then even
though they both understand that these
metrics put them in competition now it's
very difficult to expect them to sort of
magically say well I'm going to risk
half my bonus because I think it would
be better for everybody
mm-hm you have to obviously put the
organization and the teams in a position
where it makes sense for them to go in
this direction and so that might be to
say something as simple as what we're
not going to measure you on this and you
on that but we're going to measure both
of you together based on the number of
you know customers that we gain or the
the reduced number of outages that we
have but then divided by features that
we've delivered or something like that
so at least we can you know one of the
things that I wrote a a blog post that
got me shot down a few years ago which
was about no 99.99999% up time isn't
necessarily the right thing for everyone
because in most situations it comes at
the cost of your ability to innovate and
and you know speed of the change and and
stability to some extent there are two
sides of a trade-off and every company
every project maybe even
should figure out where the where they
want to set that trade off maybe their
want to try new stuff all the time and
it doesn't matter so much if it breaks
maybe their financial services company
and it's much more important that stuff
doesn't break because if it does break
then they go bankrupt all right that
changes your perspective on being risk
tolerant but no I mean I think going
back to your question what kind of
culture is needed
you need a culture that I mean and Jean
Kim obviously talked about this a little
bit you need a culture of
experimentation and learning you need a
culture that recognizes the fact that
things are not perfect we're turning
around and saying this is something we
could improve even if it's not your
personal area of responsibility is
valued and is not immediately shot down
as like trying to tell other people how
to do their job and of course not just
where such behavior is encouraged but
also where there is the ability to act
on it because even the most well
intentioned people you know once you've
given 50 suggestions and all that
happens with them is that they disappear
in the black hole of nothingness like
you give up of course
yet also yet the the culture of
experimentation actually fits very well
what we said that you cannot copycat
everybody has to find his own way
exactly and I think you're right I mean
it's not it's not possible to copy the
same solutions in the same order from
another company and that doesn't mean
maybe we should we should be carefully
that doesn't mean that for the similar
now most companies have similar kind of
problems in general like I mean the
classic ones it's impossible to get a
test environment up and running with a
realistic data set that is a problem
that 85-95 however many percent of
projects have so and if you identify
this as a problem then the solutions
aren't going to be unique to you in
general it's perfectly acceptable to
look at how other people have solved
this problem I think what what
should not be copied is the order and
the priority of those problems now for
some companies that might be the biggest
bottleneck that you have and so you
should tackle it first but that doesn't
mean that in a different context you
need to do that thing first because the
other team did it first your problem
might be that the coffee and your coffee
machine is terrible so everybody keeps
falling asleep when you're having your
production status meeting and then they
all miss the updates about the database
having blown up I mean of course that's
so that's an ironic example but it's
theirs it's not as though we can't learn
from each other it's just that the
sequence in which we need to apply in
particular no fixed particular problems
will depend a on the context or in and B
on what we're actually trying to
optimize for so I mean in the same way
like obviously if you go you know if you
take two Hospital doctors that get two
patients with the same kind of problem
you would hope that they apply more or
less the same kind of best practice
approach obviously taking into account
variables such as the age of the patient
or whether male or female or whatever
but if you get too complicated like car
crash victims which is unfortunately
typically the case of what happens in
the software develop doctors will not
treat them in exactly the same sequence
because one of them will have a broken
leg and the other one will have a
punctured lung and so you know I think
that's what really what we have to see
it's like I don't at the larger picture
the problems have different priorities
and once we can agree on what the
priorities are then we can start to say
well okay so if this is the most
important thing to solve what would be a
good solution for this do some of the
solutions that other people have tried
do they fit our problem our context or
maybe if they don't we need to try
something else so I mean and from a
software firm and since we're doing
develop software development regular
it's a bit like saying you know if
you've identified that your application
that logging is a problem obviously you
shouldn't go and write your own logging
framework
unless you've discovered that your
landscape socom a
but neither slf day nor log4j nor
commons logging or whatever will work
for you this is a job for example um but
that just because I've stated that there
are pretty good solutions for the
logging problem it doesn't mean that
every software development project now
should go and put logging at the top of
their backlog the edge of software
development movement they they wrote
down certain practices I can orient
myself and and this DevOps also offers
something like that DevOps practices
yeah I think I mean there have been a
couple of ironically enough given the
background of DevOps you know a lot of
the practices you can copy word-for-word
like know people and processes over
documentation and tools and so on so
there's a lot of that mindset carries
over I think you know some of the other
ones that have come out certainly more
recently are things like you know bear
in mind that the team isn't just
developed with an Operations personal
you know personal responsibility ability
to experiment those kind of things I
think systems thinking is a classic one
like that that is not explicitly stated
in the agile principles but I think it's
very much a concept that you know DevOps
comes up with a lot and and yeah I mean
to some extent but this is part of agile
as well like we're friends not enemies
basically ultimately we're all trying to
hopefully achieve the same thing and to
be honest you know it's easy to say that
we should all be focusing on delivering
the end-to-end system but in many
organizations that's definitely not how
things are set up so you can't really
blame a developer for saying like you're
not motivated to care about the system
in production if it's an outsourced
development company that gets paid when
they get over 35 function points and
never get to see the system in
production so yeah I mean go back to
your question so I think the Dera peen
no Jean Kim is written about a few
things John and Punk like the bar John
Willis public the bar there's a lot of
stuff out there that talks about
individual
practices that you can you can bear in
mind or you can try to pick up but to be
honest I think the agile ones fit pretty
pretty well you also talked about tools
that the tools introducing tools is the
first thing a lot of companies do but
but what is the the mandatory tool chain
is there something like a mandatory tool
chain for DevOps yeah I think I think
there is and I mean I think of course
there are always exceptions to the rule
but they're just in the same way as you
would say in general but if you're doing
software development something like a
source code repository a build tool and
an issue tracker you know you kind of
need those to do and an IDE you need
those to do development properly I think
in a similar way there is very much a
sort of standard pretty standard set of
tools now no I'm gonna name categories
of tools and in many your depending on
your architecture you may find that one
product or one open-source project
actually fulfils multiple categories so
it's not necessarily the case that you
have one tool per category but the
typical things that you see are now the
obvious ones are environment printers
and cloud management thing pretty much
all the devil stuff works on a virtual
data center to some extent whether it's
public cloud or private cloud or
whatever you almost all the things that
we try to do like spin up environments
quickly and do a lot of tests it's very
difficult to do if you're in a fully
bare mental environment and so there's
that kind of that kind of tooling on top
of that potentially depending on your
tech stack is some kind of environment
provisioning tooling so you know if
you're in a setup where instead of
having a ready baked VM or docker
container or something that has your
entire application in it but if you're
in a setup where you're like you know
your company has a standardized Linux VM
and a standardized Windows VM and then
when you ask for a server you say ok
give me a standard Linux VM and now I'm
going to put my standard app server
configuration on top of it so you
typically have a tool like a puppet or a
chef or a salt or an ansible or whatever
to do that
that's very common and then on top of
that again depending a bit on on this is
more of a question of whether you make a
conceptual distinction between your
application tier and your platform
or whether you go for the more full
stack development model you might have a
tool that you know I like to call it
puts the icing on the cake like spreads
your application tier on top of that
because in most cases an app deployment
is not necessarily the same as system
provisioning you might create an
environment that will run for maybe a
day or a week or whatever but you might
be deploying your application once per
commit and you know if it takes 25
minutes to spin up an entire environment
whereas changing you know a war file or
CLR thing or DLL might take 25 seconds
clearly you need to think about the
frequency so there's the possible
possibility of an additional layer of
like application deployment tools and
symbol is used for that I mean people
use things like Jenkins for that there's
a bunch of commercial tools for that
that you know we have one of them Excel
deploy so there's a few tools in that
space and that's more looking at it from
the system level of course now I've told
mainly about what you would have in that
testing and getting to production phase
of course once you're in production you
definitely need a bunch of monitoring
tools there's a lot of DevOps tooling
around like aggregating logs you know
things like log lis or log stash or of
course plunk there's more user level
monitoring the sort of APM style tools
and new relics and so on that don't just
try to tell you about how your servers
are running that's kind of moderately
interesting from an operational aspect
but also how are your users using your
application like you know you decided
that you were going to build this
feature because it would mean you would
get more customers in Japan or whatever
how do we know whether that's actually
true how do you find this out so people
some people use Google Analytics some
people put a lot of monitor ok so
there's that and then of course I'm
gonna shut up in a second but I mean we
could go on for a long time but I think
it
high level so the one thing that you
still need is this end to an
Orchestrator I mean it's very nice to
talk abstractly about the end-to-end
pipeline and you can draw it on a piece
of paper but at some point if you're
going to automate it you need a tool
that will actually orchestrate all the
steps I'm gonna commit a line of code
we're gonna build it I'm gonna do some
static tests that's typically what the
CI tool would do for you
but then I want to like provision a new
test environment then I want to deploy
the application and then I want to run
some functional tests and then I want to
maybe review and some load tests and
performance tests bla bla bla bla bla
bla and eventually I want to get this
thing into production and then I want to
look at it once it's got into production
to verify whether we need to roll it
back or whether we're really happy with
the result or whatever so you need this
kind of end to end process Orchestrator
as well okay interesting that also
measuring user clicks as part of the
defaults to chain well so again I mean I
think this depends you can have this
you'll get different answers depending
on who you ask I think we're certainly
if you're taking this sort of continuous
delivery process like whiteboard to a
production time approach to me this
should be very straightforward and it's
not actually you know this is for a lot
of people the focus of this initiative
is really about like how do i optimize
my supply chain like my production line
and I think it's a little ironic because
no to think of any other production line
I mean software is not that the first
industry to have the concept of a
production line like if you think about
cars or t-shirts or whatever you know
most of these organizations spend a huge
amount of money trying to understand how
their customers react to their products
because it doesn't matter if you can
have the perfect production line to
build cars in three seconds if nobody
wants to buy them they terrible who
cares exactly the software industry we
spend a lot of effort and time right now
talking about how to optimize this
process of building the software and
shipping it
but not a lot of time talking about
understanding whether it actually is fit
for purpose and the only time we find
out if it's fit for purpose or it's not
fit for purpose if it blows up it's a
very extreme case like so to me this
sort of notion of hypothesis driven
development that when you actually start
out with a feature you should ask
yourself well why are we building this
feature in the first place and that
could be a very technical hypothesis it
could be that you know if we implement
this queuing mechanism then we will be
able to handle 50% more traffic with the
same server load or whatever but it can
also be a very business level question
like if we move the shopping cart icon
from the right to the left we will get
more customers in the countries where
they read from the right to the left or
whatever so if you have that as an idea
when you start surely once you've
shipped that stuff into production you
should try to ask yourself halt was I
right or was I wrong and that's this
sort of feedback loop concept that is a
very Amin that's been from part of the
sort of agile and continuous delivery
language from the beginning it's not
just about getting it from A to B it's
about learning from B and feeding that
back into a DevOps also has quite a lot
of this often it's been more of that the
sort of the team the person level like
what from our system in production what
can we learn about how we developed it
but I think as I said you know to some
extent as teams get more comfortable
with this notion of thinking of the
end-to-end team or system or process
they start to think about what the
purpose is of what we're doing anyway
and ultimately the purpose is to ship
goods to our customers so our companies
make more money and you know everything
is great and then you have to start to
think about this stuff okay you
mentioned that it depends on the
architecture or it can depend on
architecture what tools I choose or not
are there are certain architectural
styles which support DevOps or
architectural styles which are
problematic for DevOps so I mean this
obviously of course goes back to the
question of what DevOps is yeah I think
in any landscape you can look at the
system and ask yourself where are our
problems and what can we do better but
certainly if you're if you're taking is
one of the goals like reducing the error
rate and increasing the speed at which
we can do stuff increasing the amount of
time we have to innovate on our products
rather than messing around with our
systems there there's a couple of
obviously big problem points so the one
is the classic monolithic system like
the bigger ax system you know I mean to
take a trivial example if your system
takes 8 hours to compile and ends up
with a 5 gigabyte binary that includes
half the Internet just the network time
moving stuff around is already a problem
and potentially also the cost of
downloading all this stuff more more
realistically systems that tend to be
very large and contain many components
it's very difficult to make small
changes to those systems the
environments they run in tend to be very
complicated because they contain lots
and lots of different parts some of the
technologies are very hard to automate I
mean stupid example but if you are
running on a queueing service a bus
abroad whatever which can't be put on a
virtual machine like the only machine it
runs on is a mainframe or you can't make
an emulator for it or the Installer
requires you to click through a manual
wizard those are all things that
definitely stand in the way of some
pretty common goals for DevOps such as
automation reducing error rate and so on
I think right now of course the the big
hip architecture that people are talking
about as solving all the problems where
all our previous architectures have
failed with microservices and I mean
micro-services definitely have a bunch
of if you like built-in characteristics
that supposedly make acceleration and
DevOps and these kind of things easier
yeah I heard that micro services are the
what did the first post DevOps
architectural style I was going to say
the next silver bullet but you know I
mean so I think
because there's definitely stuff in
there right and I mean ironically enough
they're not the first post DevOps
architectural style really because
they've been running in some companies
for like almost a decade now just people
didn't know about it but um so I think I
think there's definitely a few things
there that can help a lot the notion
that you should write smaller components
that are themselves easier to move
around more independent so to simply to
answer the problem of look we need to
get a test environment running where we
can verify this stuff doesn't take five
people 800 servers and a week's worth of
configuration those are all great
enablers obviously in terms of specific
micro services related technologies
containers or things people are looking
at right now partly for this reason it
makes it very easy for you to
encapsulate an entire system move it
around you know have reproducibility
across different systems so you're not
running on a different version of the
kernel here versus there I have one of
the things I say quite often is that you
don't need containers to do micro
services ironically enough a lot of
banks have a very micro service style
architecture which are simply based on
snow command-line JVM apps but they
won't have them containerized one server
will be running a hundred and fifty JVM
or Java threads basically not in an app
simple and and there to some extent that
JVM functions as Doc word if you like
it's the it's the thing that makes
things portable so there's a lot of
there's a lot of interesting advantages
that I think there's a lot of new
challenges that people are maybe wanting
to ignore and and are starting to see
happen because of course the reality is
that typically in IT so monolithic
systems have a lot of if you like extra
no unnecessary complexity calls just by
the all the different tools that are
needed and then the different people
involved and so on containers or micro
services can definitely get rid of some
of that complexity but the thing that we
sometimes like to forget is that
some of the complexity in a corner big
system is simply down to the complexity
of the business process we are trying to
model
so thinking apart an enormous monolithic
application into eighty-five micro
services will make some things easier
but those micro services still need to
talk to each other like I like to say
sometimes no microservice is an island
somewhere you wouldn't do very much so
and we've as a software development
community we spend 15 years or so trying
to figure out the problem of dependency
management within our enormous
complicated monolithic apps build time
dependencies and now we break them all
down into micro services so that removes
a lot of the build time dependencies
because you're they're small and simple
which is great but now you have the
runtime dependency problem and and if
you like proof for that statement is the
fact that there's all these container
orchestration frameworks which try to
help you do exactly that understand that
in order to get something that's
workable running you need eight or nine
of these things and you need different
versions of them when the versions have
to be compatible with all the same
problems we know from like maven if you
like they come back but they come back
at runtime so I think I think we're not
we're not out of that particular wood
yet but certainly I think you know
smaller simpler architectures can make
the the problem of getting from dev to
ops a lot easier because they also know
going back to the problems that are
common not understanding how your system
is running clearly if you're running a
container on your local machine on the
same API that's pretty much how it will
run in production you still have some
latency issues and so on but
automatically you have a level of
sharukh shared understanding that is
better then in typical setups today
where you're basically running you know
an app server inside your IDE which is
totally different from the way it runs
on a production boss I heard now you
know the tool chain and
it's easier to do their force if you
have it's probably easy if you do
micro-services that that all costs money
of course to introduce and just
wondering thus the costs are the costs
lower than the benefits I'm gonna
consult and answer applies as ever it
depends right who was it who said I mean
was it my the answer to any technically
interesting question is it depends I
think the problem here is that well the
problem I think with agile again I think
there's a lot of good lessons to learn
from agile the early adopters always
well the very early adopters do it out
of some kind of you know religious
persuasion like they don't really
necessarily ask this question they just
do it because there's somebody with a
lot of power or a lot of conviction that
can get it done and maybe the company's
growing so fast that money doesn't
really matter anyway and then you get
into that set of adopters who are not no
convinced by it if you like but who need
a business case for they need to
understand what are we going to get out
of it and I think the risk right now is
that a lot of people are doing DevOps
because they read somewhere that doing
DevOps is the next thing that they have
to do and the problem with that of
course is that they they don't really
have a clear picture of what doing
devops means certainly not for them and
be the kind of the answer often when are
we finished like when we've done DevOps
which is absurd of course because DevOps
like anything else like agile should be
a means to an end like you should be
employing these practices because they
will help you with a problem path if you
don't have a problem that you think this
thing will solve then you shouldn't be
investing any time or any money in it
like if you're releasing software as
fast as you need to
there's no production problems your
customers are happy and you don't feel
under competitive threat then yeah this
is obviously not the thing to do and I
think there's a risk there because you
know just like we are seeing agile
fatigue a lot of people having invested
a lot of money as I said in scrum boards
and post-it notes and really asking
themselves or what have we actually got
out of this I
there's a risk that that will happen
with DevOps as well and the best way to
guard against this risk as you said is
to have an idea of what you're trying to
get out of it and then going back to yes
I mean no culture of constant learning
and experimentation once you have an
idea of what your goals are and you have
some kind of metrics that you are going
to attach to those goals then you can
try something and you can start to see
whether it's taking you in the direction
that you want to go and if you're not
it's not taking you in the direction you
want to go or if it's taking you in the
right direction but for every dollar
that you make you're spending ten
dollars or whatever then I think you
really need to ask yourself or maybe
this is not the right time or the place
to be doing this so to me that is you
know starting out with a clear
conception and a shared understanding of
what your goals are and how you will
measure them and how far you want to get
in six months and how far you want to
get in a year or whatever is absolutely
essential and also throw the risks yeah
of course absolutely yeah I mean if
something blows up in production every
single time or people start leaving the
company because they don't like this way
of working yeah you know you really have
to ask yourself whether this is the
right thing for you to be doing and so
that again but obviously the risk know
these things all go together what we
were discussing earlier the notion that
you should understand the principles but
you should not try to apply a sort of
cookie cutter this company did obviously
the more you are applying a cookie
cutter approach the bigger the risk that
you don't have any no business relevant
goals of your own the bigger the risk
that you get frustrated because you're
really just trying to follow a recipe
rather than trying to optimize something
that is relevant for you and yeah I
think the other risk of course were
these things but this is a to some
extent the human problem the person who
has pushed for this the most is probably
the least likely to admit that it's not
going well so you know you and that only
makes the problem bigger because you
tend to dig yourself deeper and deeper
into the hole before eventually it
becomes
that you're stuck and it really such a
disaster that you have to give up part
of constant experimentation and learning
is there admitting that what the path we
tried isn't the right one then we try
something else and that's something in
contradiction to DevOps ironically
enough it's not even in contradiction to
something like ITIL or ITSM which were
often regarded and which suffered from
this a lot as being incredibly
prescriptive like the way to do it was
you bought the book and the book told
you exactly what you needed to do and
you had to produce 87,000 documents and
so on and so forth and of course if you
read somewhere in the fine print it said
these are all suggestions pick and
choose the ones that make sense for you
but that's of course very hard to do
it's much easier just to look at the
book and to buy the software package and
because the software package has a text
field for this particular document
exactly so that yeah I think that that's
of course a big risk with DevOps as well
and it that will only increase because
as we see no the more especially the big
vendors see that there is money to be
had here the more you see discussion of
things like DevOps stacks DevOps clouds
DevOps this DevOps that DevOps Center of
Excellence where you know somebody sees
oh we can make fifty thousand or fifty
million euros by selling this company
DevOps out of a box what about a DevOps
team yeah there's a bunch of very funny
rants about this like there is no such
thing as a DevOps team I think one of
the famous ones says something along the
lines of DevOps basically means that you
care enough about your job to give an
effing damn right so and yeah that gets
back to I think that it's much more of a
mentality a mindset but DevOps team well
I have I have sympathy with this a
little bit I think that the problem is
of course that you know really the
people who do
the tooling work in DevOps are really an
ops team like they're a platform team or
system reliability engineers or whatever
you want to call them I don't think that
matters so much well what do you call
them I think that the problem is that
for a lot of people Ops starts to sound
like the old fashioned like rack and
stack type people and so in order to
upgrade my CV because I have now I can
call it a bit and I've learned how to
use puppet or chef or whatever I need to
call myself a DevOps engineer and and we
can argue long and hard about whether
this is right or stupid or whatever the
reality to some extent has overtaken us
so I think when you talk about people
DevOps really means have a knowledge of
a particular tool set a particular skill
set and it's typically around being able
to use virtualization technologies and
an operational the new sort of breed of
ops tooling in an effective way
basically understanding development in
the up space I think yeah I would rather
obviously have you know a bunch of if
you're gonna talk about something like a
DevOps team at all they probably should
be something like a roving band of gurus
if you like who go around the company
trying to help people understand the
mindset more like coaches or trainers
okay okay and do you have materials on
DevOps you want our listeners to know
about and so while there's so many I
think if you're if you're interested in
getting a feel for the getting a feel
for the the sort of flavor of DevOps and
the mentality of some of the people who
came up with a lot of these ideas
Patrick Tobias blog post is a great
place to start Jean Kim's obviously
written a lot about this recently John
Willis and John Vincent they're both
interesting people to listen to there's
the DevOps cafe there's some interesting
podcasts there I think if you want to
get more into the like I want to
convince my management of this what are
the business cases you know what are the
arguments I can take to them that will
give me firepower to make this thing
happen in my company there is actually
some reasonably good research from some
of the bigger analysts like the
gardener's and foresters talking about
the return on investment and all these
boring terms and again you know if
you're trying to do something for your
manager more likely than not they will
not be able to tell the difference today
between DevOps and continuous delivery
so also look at some of the sort of IT
managers guide to continuous delivery is
a nice short one I mean I was the
disclaimer it's one I'm one of the
co-author so we try to distill some of
this stuff into like an 80 page guide
for some for some managers and this kind
of stuff I think that may be the best
thing you can do in terms of a fun
interactive experience is go to a DevOps
tazed Excel upstairs is a great two-day
event obviously there's a ton of meetups
you can go to as well but DevOps days
are kind of all over the world there are
two days there are community kind of
uncomfortable space ha's and you'll
really get a feel for the kind of people
that try to make up DevOps and hopefully
well you'll realize most likely that
there's much more doers there than
deciders and decision it's not like a
sort of I don't know I think of an
opposite end of the spectrum some of
those conferences where you really only
see so VP of whatever running around
trying to get our eyes it's a fun place
to be okay thank you Andrew for being on
the show
thank you very soon I want to mention
that the feedback of our listeners is
very important to us so please help us
improving our show and leave your
opinion via Twitter G+ or LinkedIn this
is when Johan for software engineering
radio
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radio net to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter
at se radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you